Mss.973.D32
American Philosophical Society
Miscellaneous documents on American history, 1681-1921
Mss.973.D32
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet 77 items
These documents are principally of Pennsylvania interest, 1757-1809, including letters to Richard I. Manning from John C. Calhoun, Marquis de Lafayette, George McDuffie, and William Wirt. There are also letters of Clement C. Biddle, James Buchanan, Francis J. Grund, James Madison, Timothy Pickering, and William H. Seward. In addition, there are several musical scores (n.d.) and 19 cancelled checks (1861-1871) drawn by Ticknor and Fields in Boston, to the order of various American authors.
77 items.
Dawes, Elizabeth F.,collector.
Box 1
Biographical/Historical Note
Elizabeth F. Dawes (1886-1989) was a collector of American documents, who sold a miscellaneous collection of American documents to the American Philosophical Society on August 29, 1957 for $350.00. She may have inherited at least part of the rich and varied collection from her father James H. Dawes, who was a scion of a wealthy and socially active Philadelphia family. His mother, who died in February 1922, was born in Sumter, South Carolina, the daughter of a Confederate soldier. She was devoted to charity and fund-raising and active in educational work, especially among young women in southern mountain districts.
Scope and Contents Note
This is a rich and varied collection of ninety-six documents on American history, spanning the years 1681-1921. A major focus is Pennsylvania, 1769-1865, including news clippings, a lottery ticket, correspondence of the Pennsylvania Revolutionary soldier Clement Biddle, the Philadelphia diplomat and editor Francis Grund; and the U.S. President and Lancaster county native James Buchanan. There are also official documents and autographs of early Pennsylvania governors. Other materials in the collection vary considerably by creator, geography and genre. The creators include (among other non-Pennsylvanians) the French Revolutionary War general, the Marquis de Lafayette; U.S. President James Madison, South Carolina governors Richard I. Manning and George McDuffie, South Carolina congressman and statesman John C. Calhoun, the longest serving U.S. Attorney General William Wirt and Lincoln’s Secretary of State William H. Seward. There are also nine musical scores (n.d.) and 19 cancelled checks (1861-1871) drawn by Ticknor and Fields Publishers in Boston, to the order of various American authors. Table of contents available.
Naval History Note
There is at least one item in this collection which may be of interest to naval historians:
Johnson, Richard M. Letter to the Secretary of the Navy. 1840 June 11. Makes a request. 1 pages.
Early American History Note
This is a collection of miscellaneous documents from early America. The earliest documents come from the early 18th century and the latest from the Civil War era. The collection contains a few documents from the revolutionary period, most of which are official governments documents or deal with business transactions. There is one long letter from Robert McPherson, a member of the Pennsylvania Flying Camp, that describes his experience. Perhaps reflecting her ancestral home, the collection contains a small but notable collection of materials from South Carolina, including a very early letter from Francis Le Jau and letters from the Marquis de Lafayette about an expected trip to South Carolina. There are a significant number of documents from Pennsylvania, especially legal documents, from the early republic. The letters from Clement Biddle, a former revolutionary war soldier, also provide insight on early national Indian relations Finally, there are also some significant autographs collected, including a Massachusetts legal form with the signature of John Adams, a letter from James Madison to the Mississippi Territory around the time of the Louisiana Purchase, and letters from Civil War era figures like John Calhoun (a rich letter in which Calhoun discusses his views on tariffs and nullification), James Buchanan, and William Seward.
Biddle, Clement C., (Clement Cornell), 1784-1855; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868; Calhoun, John C., (John Caldwell), 1782-1850; Grund, Francis J., (Francis Joseph), 1804-1863; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834; Madison, James, 1751-1836; Manning, Richard Irvine, 1789-1836; McDuffie, George, 1790-1851; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872; Ticknor and Fields.; Wirt, William, 1772-1834; American Revolution; Business Records and Accounts; Colony and State Specific History; Early National Politics; General Correspondence; Miscellaneous; Musical scores.; Native America; Official Government Documents and Records; Pennsylvania -- History -- 18th century.; Pennsylvania History; Publishers and publishing.
- Papers
  - Judgement on a case, Feb. 15, [1681]; Great Britain. Court of King's Bench
    Scope and Contents note
    Parchment. 1p. and end. Note: document on parchment mover to extra oversize storage, 3/1998. English translation of document found in regular size files.
  - Petition to the governor of South Carolina, Charles Craven, [1712?]; 12x7-1/4; Le Jau, Francis, 1665-1717
    D.S. 1p.,end.by Charles Craven. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Statement of lands to the surveyor of Dorchester county, Maryland, Jan. 24, 1757; 12x7-1/2; Green, Edward
    D. 1p.and end. (see Mrs.E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Letter to Abraham Cottenham, Trenton, July 25, 1766; 11-1/2x8; Borden, Joseph
    Bordentown, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Business.
  - 1766-1767, List of court cases
  - 1769 October 2 - 9 Newspaper fragments
  - Lottery ticket, 1773
    1 item-Pettie's Island Mill and Cash Lottery signed by Benjamin Wallace
  - Letter to David Grier, Probably 1776
    To David Grier in the Sixth Battalion of the Pennsylvania forces in Ham Morrison, Canada
  - Order to James Mease to Pay W[illia]m Irvine, Feb. 1, 1777; 9x8; United States. Continental Congress
    Philadelphia, D.S.: Rob[er]t Morris, Geo[rge] Clymer, W[illia]m Irvine, and certified as a true copy, Joseph Howell; March 20, 1787. 1p.and end. Copy. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history)
  - Letter to David Grier, Camp, June 20, 1777; 7-1/4x6; M'Pherson, Robert, 1730-1789
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Friendly letter. Concerning the war.
  - Concerning a court case over wood, March, 1779; 7x8-3/4; Pennsylvania. Attorney General's Office
    D.S.: Jonat[han] D. Sergent, Attny.Genl., Stephen Bolliet and Jno.Currie, witnesses. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes Misc.papers on Amerian history.)
  - Order to David Rittenhouse to Pay George Bryan, Nov. 5, 1779; 6x7-1/4; Reed, Joseph, 1741-1785
    Philadelphia, D.S. 1p.and end.by George Bryan. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Letter to David Greer [Grier], Oct. 5, 1780; 8x7; Davis, John, 1721-1809
    Carlisle, L.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc. Papers on American history.) Wants flour.
  - Note to William Brown, May 18, 1781; 5-1/2x6-1/2; Smith, James, ca.1719-1806
    Philadelphia, N.S.: Jas.Smith and Wm.L.Livingston. 1p.and end.by Wm.Trent. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Business.
  - Bond to Frederick Obluskey, Jan. 1, 1782; 7-3/4x9-1/2; Massachusetts
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: John Adams Treas.and M.L. Davies. 1p.,end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Deed to James Russell and Francis McNutt, March 11, 1783; 13-1/4x16-3/4; McConaughy, John
    York co., Printed D.filled in in ms. S.: John McConaughy, witnessed: Robert Chambers and Robert Chambers, jr. Entered by Archd. McClean, Recorder. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc. Papers on American history.)
  - Order to sheriff of York county, Jan. 25, 1785; 4x13-1/4; Pennsylvania
    York, Printed D.filled in in ms.S: Arch[ibal]d McClean. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc. papers on American history.)
  - Letter to [William Stevenson?], April 29, 1785; 8x6; Paca, William, 1740-1799
    L.S. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history) Business.
  - Order to the sheriff of York county, April 30, 1785; 3-1/2x14; Pennsylvania
    York, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Arch[ibal]d McClean. 1p.and end.by W[illia]m Barclay, Sheriff; July 3, 1785. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Letter to Jeremiah Van Rensselaer and Henry Stout(?), Montgomery Co., June 26, 1786; 12-3/4x8-1/4; Lansing, John, 1754-1829
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Business.
  - Order to arrest William Davis, July 4, 1786; 7-1/4x13; South Carolina. Attorney General's Office
    Charleston, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Tho[ma]s Heyward and DeSaussure. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc. papers on American history.)
  - Letter to Sir G. Yonge, Feb. 6, 1788; 9-1/4x7-1/2; Conway, Henry Seymour, 1721-1795
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers. on American history.) Business.
  - Report on Samuel Shorten, Dec., 1791; 8-1/4x6-3/4; Philadelphia. Jury
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Jared Ingersoll, Atty.Genl.and witnessed by George Hocken, George Shaffer and James West. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Letter to ----, Aug. 9, 1791; 8-3/4x7-1/4; Moultrie, Alexander
    Charleston, A.L.S. 5p.and end. Written in an abbreviated form. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Concerning public affairs.
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s Campbell, June 16, 1792; 15-1/4x9-1/2; Biddle, Clement, 1740-1814
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Arms for Indian troubles. On same sheet as letters from C. Biddle to G.McCulley and to Findlay [incomplete], of same date.
  - Letter to [William] Findlay, June 16, 1792; 15-1/4x9-1/2; Biddle, Clement, 1740-1814
    Philadelphia. L. 1p. Incomplete. (see Mrs.E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Arms for Indian troubles. On same sheet as letter from C.Biddle to McCulley and to Campbell, both of same date.
  - Letter to George McCulley, June 16, 1792; 15-1/4x9-1/2; Biddle, Clement, 1740-1814
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Arms for Indian troubles. On same sheet are letters from C.Biddle to G.Campbell and to Findlay [incomplete], both of same date.
  - Pardon granted to John Griffith, Aug. 22, 1794; 13x7-3/4; Mifflin, Thomas, 1744-1800
    Philadelphia, D.S.: Thos. Mifflin and James Trimble, Deputy Secy. 2p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Letter to the governor of Pennsylvania, June 20, 1795; 10x8-1/4; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829
    L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Concerning Indian troubles in Pennsylvania. Refers to Biddle and G.Washington.
  - Order to George Simpson to pay money to Gen. Henry Lee, Jan. 12, 1798; 4-1/2x7-1/2; Pickett, George
    Richmond, D.S. 1p.and end.by Henry Lee. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Pardon granted to James Farrell, Aug. 10, 1798; 16x10; Mifflin, Thomas, 1744-1800
    Philadelphia, Printed D.filled in in ms.S: Thos.Mifflin and James Trimble, dep. secy. 1p. and end. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Order to Peter Boynton, Dec. 30, 1799; 4x8; Smith, Thomas P., (Thomas Peters), 1777 or 8-1802
    A.D.S. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Power of attorney, Feb. 8, 1800; 13x7-3/4; Few, William, 1748-1828
    D.S. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history)
  - Letter to the governor of the Mississippi Territory, Natchez, June 5, 1804; 9-3/4x8; Madison, James, 1751-1836
    Washington, L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Forwards government publications.
  - Letter to Thomas McKean, Lancaster, March 2, 1808; 10x8; Biddle, Clement, 1740-1814
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Mrs.E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Concerning damage to public arms.
  - Autographs (2), Aug. 18, 1812; Snyder, Simon, 1759-1819
    A.D.S. 2p. Various sizes. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc. papers on American history.)
  - Commission to William Anderson, Aug. 1, 1814; 11-1/2x15-1/4; Hiester, Joseph, 1752-1832
    Philadelphia, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Joseph Hiester and James Trimble. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc. papers on American history.)
  - Autograph, Dec. 14, 1818; 3-3/4x4-1/4; Findlay, William, 1768-1846
    A.D.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Letter to ----, April, 1822; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Wirt, William, 1772-1834
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p.and end.with newspaper clipping on the death of Wirt. (see Mrs.E.Dawes. Misc.papers on America history.) Concerning a court case.
  - Letter to R[ichard] I[rvine] Manning, S.C., Dec. 15, 1824; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Will visit in March.
  - Letter to [Richard Irvine] Manning, S.D., Feb. 20, 1825; 9-1/2x7-3/4; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Concerning his tour and when he will visit South Carolina.
  - Note to [Richard Irvine] Manning, March 21, [1825]; 9-3/4x8; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Savannah, A.N.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Thank you note.
  - Letter to Richard I[rvine] Manning, Columbia, S.C., Sept. 6, 1826; 9-1/2x8; Hayne, Robert Young, 1791-1839
    Northampton, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history. Military business.
  - Letter to Julius Rhoades, July 18, 1828; 13x8; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872
    [received] A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see Mrs.E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Concerning a law case.
  - Letter to Richard I[rvine] Manning, Sumter, Sept, 1832; 10x8; Calhoun, John Caldwell, 1782-1850
    A.L.S. 5p.and add. (see Mrs.E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history) Concerning the tariff and nullification
  - Letter to Geo[rge] McDuffie, Sept., [1832]; 13-1/2x8-1/4; Manning, Richard Irvine, 1789-1836
    L.S. 1p. Copy. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Nullification. Refers to Calhoun. On same sheet as Manning to Calhoun; Sept.16,1832.
  - Letter to John C[aldwell] Calhoun, Sept. 16, 1832; 13-1/2x8-1/4; Manning, Richard Irvine, 1789-1836
    Fulton, L.S. 1p.and end. Copy. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Nullification issue. On same sheet is copy of letter from Manning to McDuffie; [Sept.1832].
  - Letter to Rich[ar]d I[rvine] Manning, Columbia, S.C., Oct. 22, 1832; 9-3/4x7-1/2; McDuffie, George, 1790-1851
    Cherry Hill, A.L.S. 5p.and add. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Concerning tariffs and nullification.
  - Letter to the Secretary of the Navy, Washington, June 11, 1840; 10x8; Johnson, Richard M. (Richard Mentor) 1780-1850
    [answered] A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Mrs.E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Makes a request.
  - Letter to ----, March 8, 1841; 10-1/2x7-1/2; Young, Richard Montgomery, 1796-1852
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Friendly letter.
  - Mortgage of Slaves, Feb. 7, 1842; 18x13; Manning, John L. (John Lawrence), 1816-1889
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S. 1p.and end.by various officials. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc. papers on American history.)
    General note
    See oversize
  - Letter to Mrs. Plitt, Aug. 26, 1845; 8x5; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Walter Underhill, New York, March 26, 1849; 7x4-1/2; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see Mrs. E.Dawes, Misc.papers on American history) Acknowledges receipt of letter.
  - Note to Edward B. Merrell, Aug. 2, 1850; 10x8; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872
    Washington, A.N.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Acknowledges receipt of letter.
  - Letter to Charles Brown, April 7, 1853; 10x8; Grund, Francis J., (Francis Joseph), 1804-1863
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Asks his help for an unfortunate man, Christopher Hildebrand.
  - Autograph, June, 1856; 7-3/4x5; Aiken, William, 1806-1887
    A.D.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Autograph, April 7, 1856; 6-1/2x7-1/4; Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss, 1816-1894
    A.D.S. 1p.with note by A.R."Boss" Shepherd. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc. papers on American history)
  - Letter to Cornelius & Baker, Philadelphia, Jan. 31, 1857; 7-1/2x8; Reeder, Andrew H. (Andrew Horatio), 1807-1864
    Easton, A.L.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history) Business.
  - Autograph, Nov. 26, 1857; 3-1/2x5-1/2; Harris, Johann G
    A.D.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Autographs (2), Feb. 28, 1860; 2-3/4x7-3/4; Moore, Thomas Overton, 1804-1876
    A.D.S. 1p. (see Mrs.E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history)
  - Cancelled checks to various persons, May 7, Nov. 9, 1861-1872; Atlantic Monthly
    D. 1p.each and end. Various sizes. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Checks made out to: James R.Lowell, Mrs. H.B. Stowe, Mrs. Harriett E. Prescott, H.T. Tuckerman, H.W. Longfellow, G. Ticknor, T.B.Read, Mrs. S.Hawthorne, J.F.Trowbridge, O.W.Holmes, J.G.Whittier, J.Parton, Celia Thaxter, A.D.T. Whitney, W.H.H. Murray, Miss M.A. Dodge, Bayard Taylor, E.P. Whipple, Constance F. Woolson.
  - Promissory note to William Mills, April 15, 1865; 3x8, 10-3/4x8-1/2; Robarts, W S
    Germantown, A.D.S. 1p. Attached to notary's protest of note, signed: Charles B.Engel, Notary. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc. papers on American history.)
  - Promissory note to William Mills, April 22, 1865; 3-1/2x8, 10-3/4x8-1/2; Robarts, W S
    Germantown, A.D.S. 1p. Attached to notary's protest of note, signed: Charles B.Engel, Notary. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Letter to William H. Seward, Washington, Dec. 21, 1865; 10x8; Manning, John L. (John Lawrence), 1816-1889
    Printed L.filled in in ms.S. 1p. Copy. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Acknowledges pardon. Contained in folder with: U.S. State dept. Certification...; Jan. 15, 1866.
  - Certification of authenticity of copy of letter by John L. Manning to W.H.Seward, Jan. 15, 1866; 10x8; United States. Dept. of State
    Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: W[illiam] Hunter. 1p.and enc. Seal. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Contains copy of letter from Manning to Seward; Dec. 21, 1865.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Steele, Pittsburgh, Feb. 23, 1867; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Yates, Richard, 1815-1873
    Washington, L.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Concerning the temperance society.
  - Letter to Brown Manning, June 23, 1869; 7x4-1/2; Johnston, Joseph E. (Joseph Eggleston), 1807-1891
    Savannah, A.L.S. 3p. (see Mrs. E. Dawes. Misc.papers on American history) Business. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to James H. Dawes, Philadelphia, May 1, 1921; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Locke, William
    Cannes, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.) Thank you note.
  - Address to James W. Fletcher, undated; 3x5; Bigler, William, 1814-1880
    Philadelphia. A.D.S. 1p. (see Mrs. E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Autograph., undated; 1x3; Ritner, Joseph, 1780-1869
    A.D.S. 1p. (see Mrs.E.Dawes. Misc.papers on American history.)
  - Autographs (2)., undated; Shulze, John Andrew, 1775-1852
  - Autograph., undated; 3/4x1-1/2; Wolf, George, 1777-1840
  - The Caledonian Laddy: A Favorite Scottish Song, undated; Unidentified (Box Oversize)
    See Oversize
  - Oh Say Simple Maid, undated; Unidentified (Box Oversize)
  - Aurora Dawns: A Chinese Air with an Accompaniment for the Piano Forte, undated; Unidentified (Box Oversize)
  - The Strings to your Bow, Undated; Unidentified (Box Oversize)
  - The Kiss, undated; Unidentified (Box Oversize)
  - I'm in Haste, undated; Unidentified (Box Oversize)
  - Within a Mile of Edinburgh Town A Favorite Scottish Song, undated; Unidentified (Box Oversize)
  - When the Mind is in Tune, undated; Unidentified (Box Oversize)
  - O Innocence Celestial Maid (Box Oversize)